[Music]
welcome to part two of my optimizing
hydration for athlete series
now in part one i talked about how basic
recommendations like
drink half your body weight in ounces
per water or go to the
internet and find a hydration calculator
to figure out how much water you need to
drink
those systems are okay but they're far
from being ideal
we can do a lot better i guess is the
point right so more specifically we
talked about
all these things you see in white in the
first video so if you missed that one
go ahead and hop back now i would
strongly encourage you do that before
you watch this video
but if you're a good little boy or girl
and you've already watched video one and
you're here for video two
this is what we're going to get into so
i'm going to talk more specifically
about how hydration works
physiologically and biochemically
how that all happens in your body and
why certain things are actually needed
we'll talk about how to identify how
much you sweat whether you're a high
sweater low sweater moderate
and what's actually in your sweat high
salt low salt content how do you figure
that out and then what does that mean
right in other words why do we should we
not just be telling everyone to drink
the same things
before during or after their workouts
right needs to be
individualized we'll talk about sports
drinks and electrolyte packs more
specifically
i'll go through a bunch of them and i'll
show you what's in each one and how they
differ
and then which one you should choose
based on what you found out about how
your own personal sweat
rate and content works and then finally
and perhaps
most importantly we will enter and
discuss
our final two of my criminally
underrated mc's i hit one to three in
the first part of the video
and now i'll hit the last two in this
discussion
right if i had to actually summarize all
of video one
i'd say we covered the first part of
this sentence
how much water to drink how many fluids
to drink and how that differs based on
your body type training
how hard you're working and all the
things go into answering part one how
much
but we never discuss what that's the
import that's the entire point of video
two
so we know the answer is clearly not
that right you don't wanna just drink
water again not that it's necessarily
bad but it's not
optimal that's the whole point we want
to maximize our performance
or get as close to that as we can so the
basic thing we have to consider here is
this
you aren't sweating out water so when
you look on your skin and when you see
it on your shirt you're like oh my gosh
that's water no it's sweat
and so you can't just drink back water
you need to drink back sweat
in order to figure out then what we need
to do we have to have a nice lengthy
in-depth complicated discussion about
what is in sweat
how our body works how hydration works
physiologically and then what to do
about that
so that's what we're going to get into
in the next section here
if you're sort of dozing off or you're
not fully engaged right now i would get
up
go chug a gallon of water maybe go run a
sprint two or three miles
i don't know do something but you got to
come back when you're focused and ready
to go
i know i'm ready to go right now i'm
raring are you
if you're not get the hell out of here
and come back when you are
all right you're here okay let's party
humans have on average about two and a
half million sweat glands throughout
their entire body
and for some reason they're actually
highly concentrated in your feet
there's estimates are in the range of
about 250
000 of them just in your little feetsy
there which is one of the reasons why
some of you got stank ass feet
in fact actually you know it's totally
off topic here but my two-year-old
tatiana she loves i created i showed her
this funny little joke where
every time she takes her socks and shoes
off she'll take him and put him up to
her nose and be like ew
p.u stinky and then she actually like
acts like she's eating me all she's like
oh i'm eating my socks yucky it's
hilarious
so she's two and has already figured out
that feet stank right that's probably
why too many sweat glands down there
but physiologically how the whole
process works i talked about in part one
the human body is somewhere between 50
and 70 percent mostly between 50 and 60
percent
total water the rest is solid and if we
break down that water content we put it
into three
big categories and in fact i'll actually
make those
three in the two big categories right so
category one is what we call the icf or
intracellular fluid
category two is the ecf or extracellular
now intracellular is exactly what it
sounds like it's the fluids that are
inside of your cells
so of all the water in your body about
two-thirds of it or 66 percent
is inside your cells that's the vast
majority of where we hold it
the remaining two thirds or remaining
third rather is in the extracellular
fluid and the ecf is comprised of two
things interstitial and plasma
interstitial is basically the space in
between all your cells
and about 80 of that third is an
interstitial space so
translation of all the water in your
body the vast majority of it is in your
cells
a lot less is in between your cells and
then some of it's in your blood but
that's a very small percentage
okay so from here on out i'll refer to
those as icf and ecf
or i'll potentially say interstitial and
plasma but those are your three major
distinctions
with that in mind then when we're
talking about maximizing hydration we
know that our the biggest
emphasis needs to be getting fluids into
the cells
okay losing some interstitial fluid is
probably survivable
and we don't want to lose plasma fluid
either but the real driver here again 66
percent has got to go into the tissue
itself
if we then do things like just chug
straight water and we greatly expand our
plasma fluid we may have solved the
problem
there but unless we got that water to go
into the tissue
we haven't really solved the bigger
problem
so how sweat works specifically let's
get into some detail
okay now as i mentioned we have our icf
right here and then on the outside what
you're seeing this black line is
important because that
represents the cell membrane or the
outside of the cell i think that stops
it from being the interstitial fluid
okay
outside of that like i said you've got
your plasma
and the interstitial space in between
take the interstitial and the plasma
combine them together and we've got your
ecf now outside of your plasma actually
and more specifically the capillaries is
where your fat and skin layer happens
your sweat glands are of course then
embedded in your fat and skin they go
all the way down and make some kind of
contact with the plasma
and that's how you take things put them
in the blood get them into the sweat
glands
and then get them out of your actual
body that's the basic process
of all the things that are inside each
one of these categories it's very
important we understand
what is and where and in what rough
concentrations you don't have to know
the exact amount but you have to know
how it is relative to the other
compartment
for example if we take our first
electrolyte
chloride first and foremost you see it
has a little dash there which means it
has a negative charge and that's going
to be very important later
but we see actually there's a lot of
chloride more of it in the interstitial
space and then some of it in plasma
so if you're going to look at a basic
concept of gradients in osmosis
if this membrane was wide open right if
there was no blocking here
then some of that chloride would want to
go inside the cell so that it would
balance it out instead of being three
and one it'd be two and two
this is how hydration works that's the
most basic concept right
we have to balance osmosis and diffusion
with a couple of other things that we'll
get into
our next thing that's of importance is
potassium
right k plus and about 98 of the
potassium in our body is actually in our
cells so it's a huge concentration there
with a little bit of it being out in the
interstitial space and
of course some little amount is in the
plasma as well
we also have our third most important or
third important component here
which is n a or that sodium of course
there's a little bit of sodium inside
the cell but the vast majority
of it is actually in the ecfn plasma now
all of you that have had exercise
physiology class you're like oh yes
action potential
electrochemical gradient all that stuff
yes but you may not realize how
important that stuff is in hydration
okay so this is basically what we're
looking at
now we also realize we've got i'm
calling it glucose here but
you know that when we store
carbohydrates in a
in cells it's not glucose we store in
the form of glycogen okay but just to
keep things a little
simpler i'm calling it glucose we also
know that you've got some amount of
glucose in your blood
remember baseline here i'm going to show
you why this is important in a second
okay so if you were to kind of highlight
this in the top you can see there that
the
intracellular is basically a whole bunch
of potassium with a little bit of
chloride and a tiny bit of sodium
and the plasma equal almost equal parts
sodium and chloride
and a lot less potassium now sweating is
basically when you start taking the h2o
or the water
from the plasma you put it into these
sweat glands and you begin to move it
from there through that little channel
out and it starts to bead up outside you
continue to do that and the sweat
the water pulls up on the outside but
importantly it's not
only water granted it's a high
percentage of water so if you were to
look inside that
droplet you would see that it is about
99 h2o
but it's about one percent sodium
chloride potassium magnesium and calcium
and you can see what i'm depicting there
the vast majority of the electrolytes in
your water
are sodium a little bit less chloride
and then a whole lot less potassium a
whole lot less magnesium and then trace
in very small amounts of calcium
so if we're to think about this in the
context of hydration now we know that we
need to drink things that are in large
part water
right this is mostly what we're losing
but we need a lot of sodium a lot of
chloride maybe a little bit of potassium
and then potentially some magnesium and
i guess maybe you could consider calcium
but it's not really important because
that number is really really really
small
so coming back to our image here what
we're really looking at
is this our sweat is actually oh look at
that
what do you notice about our sweat
the contents of it and the contents of
the plasma
hmm interesting right
as i said at the beginning you're
sweating out sweat not water so you
don't want to drink back water you want
to drink back sweat
which now that you know the contents of
the sweat you know that it needs to be
in large part
sodium and chloride and a little bit of
potassium like i said maybe some
magnesium
well you're probably jumping the gun a
little bit here so i'll spill the beans
but
if you were to take a sodium molecule
combine it with a chloride molecule
we would call that new molecule
sodium chloride street name
salt so if you were to just simply take
some water add a couple of pinches of
salt to it
you would actually get a lot closer than
just drinking it
now we tend to call these combinations
of ions like sodium potassium chloride
that have charges on them like pluses
and minuses we call these the
electrolytes
that's all electrolytes are basically
sodium chloride potassium
right and maybe even some magnesium
these are the primary players
so really your sweat process doesn't
look like what i represented it actually
looks more like a combination of that
right where some of those ions would be
in concentration in the things that's
sweated out and that's what's actually
going to be on your skin
and this is why if you've ever had a dog
and and you sweat a little bit you go
over your dog your it loves to come over
and lick the sweat off because it's a
bunch of salt water and animals like
that
oh it's also why you can put salt licks
out for cows and deer and things like
that and they run up to it because they
know how important it is
to get that salt in okay so
like i said lots of water and lots of
sodium and chloride are lost from the
ecf with sweat
so oh enter the problem here we used to
look like this
okay now we look like this
and so in order to optimize hydration if
we're not careful
we've dropped our sodium content a lot
from the
the interstitial fluid which is supposed
to be very concentrated so now it's
actually very similar to the
concentration
in the cell the icf when we lose that
gradient
sodium doesn't no longer wants to rush
inside the cell potassium no longer
wants to rush outside the cell
and that's problematic because that's
what we have to have to cause muscle
contraction
now i guess in the most extreme
if this was the cardiac tissue and not
the muscle you're probably thinking of
cardiac being also muscle just a
different kind if there's no electrical
chemical gradient there
we no longer have a concentration
gradient we no longer have contraction
your heart stops beating so i guess in
you know too in fact i don't even plan
to go into this but you all remember dr
koborkin right dr death the guy that was
one of the most famous positions
uh for helping physician-assisted
suicides he would basically give people
a giant bolus
an iv basically of potassium he would
hook it up to him right and he would say
all right whenever you're ready just
turn it on he would get huge
dumps of potassium here the
concentration of potassium on the
outside of the cell on the inside of the
cell became
equal and so these sodium and potassium
things didn't want to exchange so even
when the channels were open
they didn't move anywhere no gradient no
muscle contraction and you slowly sort
of drift off to sleep
and your heart stops beating right
that got kind of morbid interesting
though right okay
well anyways kind of back to here the
same thing you can imagine
happening now with either a high extreme
increase in concentration of potassium
or a decrease in concentration of sodium
now if you go back to video one i talked
about yeah people become dehydrated but
another mistake folks make
even during exercise and competition is
over hydrating
so imagine that you didn't even
necessarily lose the sodium
or you lost some of it but you you drank
back way too much water
you get what we call hypoatremia which
is low
natremia and a low sodium concentrations
that are caused
not usually by losing too much sodium
but drinking way too much pure water
so the concentration here becomes
extremely dilute
it doesn't have any difference between
here and here in sodium so nothing
happens and then the muscle stops
contraction
and this is why again almost every year
we see somebody
in a triathlon or a marathon or some
endurance event like that actually
die from drinking too much water during
the event right they lose that
concentration gradient
things get too diluted on the outside
and we have a problem
all right so if we want to maximize our
hydration status we need to make sure
that we're drinking back
something that we call iso osmotic so
something that is the same
it kind of like concentration it's not
the same but we'll just call it that for
now
something that is the same concentration
as what we lost
that's in the ecf if we do that then we
can expand the total volume here
and we can continue to do that and we
won't have any problems with
concentrations if we only drink back
something that is too
dilute or something too concentrated
something too salty
then we're going to have problems so i'm
going to walk you through the physiology
behind each one of those scenarios
okay let's start right here now here's
what happened
remember this is our starting state here
okay actually going back to there
everything was nice and happy here we
started to sweat we know we started to
lose a ton of water
so the total volume of the area your
plasma as well as interstitial space
goes down wait we've lost water right
water is what gives it
its space we started to lose water and
we started to lose some of the gradients
so look what happens to the total
volume boom
there right not the volume of the plas
of the fat and skin but the plasma and
the interstitial space go down
okay so we've lost content and we've
lost total volume
no good well because we've lost so much
water
we lost more water than we lost
electrolytes we lost
volume and we increased concentration so
now the outside of our cells
ecf is concentrated and low volume
now when you think about osmosis and
diffusion
right and you know the basic principles
i'm not going to walk you through
what would then happen what would the
cell membrane
do given that it is permissible to
water well things are going to want to
go from
here to there well things more
specifically being water
when you do that the volume of the ecf
returns or increases
the concentration goes down because
you're putting more water in it
but now the volume of the icf goes down
and the concentration goes up
and however much water you've lost from
here will determine how much you move
from the icf
right so a little bit of loss okay fine
basically the ecf
or icf says okay we'll cover you we'll
go down a little bit in our volume
we'll we can afford increasing our
concentration a touch until we reach
equilibrium
you continue to do that though you're
going to continue to lose
water from the cell and this is how your
cells become dehydrated even though
you're sweating from your plasma
right and as i mentioned given the fact
that most of our water is supposed to be
in our cells if you continue to do that
you can see how the cells will lose or
contractile function very quickly
you're going to lose performance when
muscles can contract whatever it is
power strength speed accuracy
right we talked about all these things
actually in the first video
endurance i mean you name it it's going
to go down and you start losing
volume and increasing concentration in
the ucf right so water is going to want
to go that direction
until it reaches something like that
okay
so we've now got low volume and high
concentration of both the icf and ecf
so to summarize all that the results of
sweating are this both inside and
outside of the cell are low volume
meaning water and high concentration
meaning too much sodium potassium and
chloride
so if you want to put some more specific
numbers to this this is what we're
looking at
what's in one liter of sweat and
remember one liter is
2.2 pounds all right 1000 milliliters
the same thing
okay this is probably what we're looking
at on average people range somewhere
between 500 and 2000 milligrams 2000
milligrams would also be two grams
of potassium and about a fourth of that
in our sodium of sodium and about a
fourth of that in potassium
now a probably a very fair way to think
about this is it's a generally a four to
one
salt sodium to potassium ratio therefore
what you put back in should be somewhat
close to that ratio
so as we get you know down the talk a
little bit and we start looking at
different
hydration products we're going to want
to make sure that we're close to these
ratios
now having said that look at a couple of
things on there
i know that for example major league
baseball teams often times in pre-season
they will
hire a company there are several of them
but
these companies will come out and it
will do it put a little patch on your
arm
and it will measure not only your sweat
rate but sweat content and they'll
figure out are you closer that 500
milligram
potassium of sodium are you closer to
that thousand or two thousand
um now if you're say in the thousand
milligrams
or or one gram per liter of your sweat
that's what we would call kind of a
moderate number uh
1500 would be a little bit higher 2000
would be would be pretty high i'm not
sure i've seen many folks that high
and 5000 would be pretty low so i guess
if you wanted if you're like i don't
know
i have no way to test it um and i'll
talk about things you can buy later
probably starting off that either
between 1000 or 1500 would be the
assumption okay and then just divide
that by four
that's probably where you're at for your
potassium
chloride actually tends to mimic sodium
pretty well as we talked about
for several reasons right stoichiometry
of
of salt is one sodium one chloride
your sweat is actually pretty similar so
whatever you have in
sodium you can assume that it's probably
similar in chloride as well
sometimes it's a little bit higher but
you know again if you get that measured
specifically then you'll know
that's either way in terms of magnesium
and calcium they are often
super negligible i mean you're talking a
10th
or 20th of the amount of magnesium as
you're probably going to sweat and
sodium chloride
so really we're talking about the big
three sodium chloride and potassium
having said that it is pretty common for
folks to be low in magnesium so it's not
the worst thing
ever to add some magnesium to your
hydration thing it's not
probably a huge component of your sweat
but if you're going to add a bunch of
electrolytes
and you're going to drink something
specifically this is a good chance i
guess to add some magnesium to your diet
so not the worst thing ever
all right so i'll walk you through this
this case study i guess here let's say
this individual athlete
was doing a hard track workout and he
lost four and a half pounds in
a one-hour track workout okay that would
be
how many liters two right roughly two
liters
uh four and a half pounds per hour is a
very normal
kind of upward end but not not not that
crazy
um for 165 70 pound athlete to lose four
and a half pounds and
outside okay not not incredibly
difficult so i didn't pick an extreme
example
in fact i would call this a somewhat
normal maybe slightly higher
than normal but nothing crazy work out
his absolute numbers would probably look
like something like this it's somewhere
between one to four grams and i know i
switched units on you for sodium but i'm
part of what i'm trying to do with these
videos honestly is teach units so
don't tell my students that right but
anyways
a thousand milligrams one gram you get
it by now okay
uh you would see how many how much
potassium there as well as a chloride
uh and magnesium okay so then this is a
specific amount
um we would say okay you lost this much
weight we know that there's this much
concentration there
therefore this is exactly how much of
these electrolytes we need to put back
in your body
now if you drink water straight you're
going to get the h2o part but you're not
getting any of the sodium chloride or
potassium
so again i mean like i don't want you to
think oh my gosh if i drink water after
my workout i'm gonna i might die
that's probably extremely unlikely
however you're not optimizing the
situation okay so we can do better than
that
i've talked about this a little bit but
let me show you specifically what this
concept of hyponatremia really is
so if you can imagine coming back into
here okay
now we talked about when you sweat how
we reduce that total volume of the ecf
well if you drink back too much water
you do the opposite right so now our
volume gets extreme and our
concentration goes down
okay so again a common mistake
hyponatremia is not usually because of
low salt intake
and it's not because of excess salt loss
it's almost always a function of
excess pure water intake okay don't get
tripped
or tricked on a quiz question about that
okay too dilute is the issue no gradient
there therefore we have problems okay
if you do that in theory the water
should start to go back
into the cell okay osmosis the same
thing would happen when we went the
other direction right so it should be
floating back in there but that actually
doesn't happen
okay what
yeah it doesn't work that way some folks
would think oh my gosh
i want to get a maximum high volume in
my ecf
then that will push water back into the
icf rehydrating it
and everything would balance out but
that's not how it works
because of a little thing we have to
talk about
called the raas right or the
renin angiotensin aldosterone system
okay now this is actually pretty
complicated so i'm going to give you the
super condensed version basically it is
you have these things in your body this
stuff in your body called aldosterone
and that effectively helps you hold on
to sodium
on the opposite end of that you've got a
thing called the antidiuretic hormone
adh and that tells you to hold water
okay so now this is something we
manipulate in weight cut scenarios with
our combat support athletes right so we
can do what's called water loading we
can
manipulate the aldosterone and adh
systems and then they will just
sit around and basically start peeing
and peeing and peeing and their weight
will come down
the reason we can do that is because the
point or one of the major points of adh
and aldosterone is to monitor and
regulate
fluid and sodium so when you start
messing with both of those you start
messing with the amount the activity and
the sensitivity of aldosterone adh
and you get a pretty particular
physiological response which is just
this okay so if you start to become
hyper hydrated again whether you're
water loading because of sport or you're
say drinking way too much water
that's two to loop and we have that
expansion you have excess fluids right
so as a result of that you see a
decrease in adh and aldosterone
the result of that is a decrease in
sodium and water
retention right in other words diuresis
so your body says whoa way too much
fluid
let's reduce how much sodium and water
we're holding on to because we know
sodium also helps you hold onto water
okay so too low sodium diet you're going
to pee things out because you're too
concentrated too high you're going to
hold water
right so during our rehydration process
we want a lot of sodium to help us keep
our water
but if again you just drink way too much
water those hormones go down
sodium your body gets a signal says hey
stop first of all get rid of the water
we've got too much and then second start
getting rid of sodium
because we're holding on to too much
water as it is and we know that that
will further the situation
so physiologically you start dumping
those two things and increasing
uh by the way for the record increase in
potassium also has the same diuretic
effect okay so this is another way that
you can
sort of cheat the system if you're super
water loaded or something just bump
up the potassium and that's going to
help you pee more right sodium makes you
hold on to water potassium does the
opposite right
so this again like i mentioned this is
exactly how water loading works
alright so if we go back to our figure
here
we know that post exercise somewhere
between
25 to 50 percent of the water you drink
will be lost in urine
so let's say you go back to that
original thing and you lost four and a
half pounds of fluid
well if you drink four and a half pounds
of water straight back
you then are gonna pf 25 to 50 percent
of that
two two and a half pounds your actual
net result is you only drink back
half the water that you lost which means
you're still dehydrated and this happens
again because
we drink too much water too fast we get
a great expansion of the ecf
high volume low dilution the body thinks
hey
we got excess water here because it came
in so fast
now let's urinate it so before we had
time
to put the water back into the cell
we actually start peeing it out so here
we are sitting there
dehydrated in our cells too much water
in our plasma
and you start peeing it out rather than
moving it into the cell because you
drank too much
too fast and it was too dilute all right
this also has a problem for a number of
other reasons number one it gives you a
false sense of hydration why could you
chug a bunch of water five minutes later
you go pee and it's crystal clear and
you're like yep i'm hydrated
nope you over drink water you drink it
too quickly
also since you smash so much water it
cuts down the amount of saliva signal
you get
and the thirst sensation goes down so
your it your body own body tells you
we're good here bro don't drink any more
water so you stop
feeling like you need to drink water
despite the fact you're actually peeing
out half what you just drank and your
total hydration status is not recovered
so you're really fighting yourself and
hopefully i'm kind of guiding you toward
a solution i've been hinting at
how you solve that problem
okay so again we talked about in the
first video
when we look at athletes we see that
they typically
under rehydrate by about 50 so if you
lose a liter in
exercise most athletes if you just don't
do anything will only drink back half a
liter
almost identical to the amount that
we're getting there right so you combine
that with the fact that
i'm not drinking enough pure water i'm
not drinking enough fluids as it is
supposed to work out
and half that's being lost well the net
result is you only get about a 25
or so percent rehydration
not a good thing right so
the fluid must be at the same
concentration as the icf
or if it's too dilute right like i said
we're going to pee that out if it's too
concentrated we can see the opposite
so you can pull water out of the cell
actually if it's too concentrated so you
imagine
the outside being small super
concentrated will actually continue to
drive more fluid out of the cell
to change the concentration uh in the
ecf right
so you could further the problem in
addition you can give yourself diarrhea
so so when you ingest something that is
really really concentrated super salty
that salt gets your intestines before it
gets all the way out of your gut right
so some of that gets in there and now
you actually made your intestines
incredibly concentrated which means it's
going to pull water into your intestines
and your digestive tract well you know
what happens when you get
fluid in your digestive tract you get
explosive diarrhea
i don't know i guess you didn't have to
be explosive but diarrhea nonetheless
right
so again you're dehydrated and now
you're going to get
diarrhea which exacerbates that
dehydration even more
so you have to know what you're doing in
fact i could tell you a
number of professional athletes in
weight cut and weight class sports
who get diarrhea almost every time they
go through the rehydration process
because they don't know what they're
doing
okay so you really want to make sure
concentration is dialed here right you
can see problems on both sides
all right oh what's that
you've seen number four on the screen
which could only mean one thing
my fourth in my list of five criminally
underrated indices and this one
is a bit of a cheat because i actually
have
two people on here and i picked them
because i figured
it's a bit unfair people know them but i
think at this point in my life it kind
of breaks my heart because
they're more known for their acting than
they actually are their hymns their
emceeing
which sucks because they're actually
super legitimate
emcees so i wanted to make sure that you
all knew out there
fresh prince will smith iced tea yeah
you know them they're like hollywood
actors maybe
no they are both incredibly legit in
fact every damn time i listen to an ic
song i'm like
man he's so underrated the guy is so
good go back and look up his history a
little bit but
but he started a whole revolution a
whole style of rapping
that is still going on today in fact
it's the predominant style of rapping
no one really gives him credit for doing
it people don't realize what he actually
started they give
other people credit for it but if you
get in the know and those people who get
credit say no no it was iced tea
ice is the one that did it still active
today occasionally
and then fresh prince like go back and
listen to his first couple albums
flawless just flawless if the guy never
acted in his life he still would have
been an all-time great emcee just
incredibly talented
uh he's yeah it's just insane how good
that dude is um
so many so many classic songs once we
get into like the
like will smith like 2000 era we start
to fade but when he was a
jazzy jeff who's another legendary dude
um those first like i said two or three
albums are just
it's incredible um there's a lot of mcs
out there right now
that will smith would smash no question
right
all right anyways back to our carlos
so like i said our sweat replacement
fluid should contain what is in
ourselves specifically
these four items and at ideally a
similar concentration or osmolality
so if we go back to here how much of
each goes into it remember the example i
gave you was
our athlete lost four and a half pounds
we'll call it two liters
that was the concentration and
everything well we also forgot to add
our glucose
okay so we need to add back those
numbers plus a little bit
of sugar in the same amount that we lost
and here's what that means
like i've been saying this is actually
sodium periodic table that's n a
and i've circled a little thing over
here which is a fun little trick that
you probably don't care about but i
think is really cool so we know that the
molecular weight of sodium is we'll call
it 23
okay well
if i know i've lost and i've sweat out a
thousand milligrams of
sodium per liter right let's just say
you had an average
sodium concentration rate
well can i just go out put sodium in my
water i guess well no you can't
it's very you can't put things in your
body that aren't neutralized
so you rarely can get something that has
a positive or a negative charge
they almost always have to be made into
a salt right so
that basalt basically happens when you
take a positive and a negative combiner
together and neutralizes a charge and
that's how we have to deliver
that's why whenever you take magnesium
or calcium
all these things they have to be
actually in a different form because
they have to neutralize
so again our problem is we know we have
to bring
sodium back into the body but we can't
do
straight up n a so how do we get that
back in of course our answer is
our friend chloride turns out it's nice
in the fact that we also lose almost
equal pounds
parts chloride and we know a specific
molecule
or combination i guess that is one part
sodium
one part chloride now here's where the
math gets a little bit funny
since the salt is those two things but
chloride actually has a molecular weight
that's almost
twice sodium so it's something like 43
or something like that
the total weight between the two is a
little bit different it's almost a two
to one combination right
so in other words if you need like say
500 milligrams
of sodium you actually have to give them
about 1.5 grams of salt to make the math
work
all right you follow me there let me
walk you through okay
so we have about two and a half times
the milligrams of sodium to equal the
amount of salt we need that's the easier
way to do it
right so if you need again a thousand
milligrams of
sodium to replace because that's your
sweat rate
we need to have about two and a half
times the milligrams of sodium that you
need in salt
which in this case would be about 2.5
grams
okay so the translation of all that
would go okay
you are estimating you're a moderate
salt sweater
which mean would be a a gram per liter
you need to then put back about 2.5
grams of
salt because of that two to one
molecular weight ratio you know that
salt is gonna although it's one part
each
right that 3.5 molecular weight of the
chloride is going to mean that
it's heavier weighted more biased
towards the chloride so you need to come
up to two and a half grams or so in salt
to get your one gram of sodium
that makes sense uh that wasn't the
smoothest delivery i've ever had
but i hope after repeating it six times
you started
to kind of get there all right again if
the molecular stuff weight stuff just
threw you for a whack just go back to
the equation here on the board okay i
didn't mean
to make things more complicated than it
had to be usually
i think i feel like i do a pretty good
job of doing the opposite but i mean i
lost you there
okay now i've mentioned this a couple of
times you may be thinking yourself well
how do i know if i'm a heavy salt
sweater outside of actually going and
get it physically tested
one thing you need to do is just simply
look at your outfit look at your clothes
if you finish a workout i actually
recommend people wearing a hat
the first time if they want to try this
give it a day or so or whatever when the
thing tries look at the color
if you see white all over the place
or you see no white or you see just like
covered in white
that's basically going to tell you how
much salt is in your content right so
a a white person that's got white all
over your gear all the time you would
assume you're probably more like that
1500 milligram folks
high salt sweater if there's nothing
ever if it's just wet and then it's
dried and nothing on it at all then you
may be close to the 100
or the thousand milligram or maybe even
500 milligram and you could play it from
there right
so maybe give yourself two and a half
grams
of salt in that if that you know based
on the equation here
maybe go down to two maybe try three in
the day it's pretty close
so it's not that big a deal oh for the
record
you don't think about salt in terms of
grams
if you take a half a teaspoon of salt
that's going to be about two and a half
grams of salt
and you know that then therefore is
going to be about one gram of sodium
so if you think you're a thousand
milligram per liter person you do it
so you did a workout you weighed
yourself at the beginning of the workout
to the end of the workout you lost
2.2 pounds you think you're a medium
salter therefore you need to you know
you need to replace half a teaspoon
of salt in your water all right so i
just took you down from chemistry
all the way through practical
application of how much salt to put in
your water
and it wasn't that complicated again if
you're a higher person double
that you may have to go up you may have
to go to three quarters of a teaspoon
or a full teaspoon if you think you're a
real high salt sweater
don't make the mistake though of
teaspoon versus tablespoon
you're gonna poop yourself all over the
place it's not gonna feel good
right and since we're here i'm not gonna
leave you hanging three teaspoons is one
tablespoon like i said so
if you're trying to shoot for one
teaspoon and you actually get
one tablespoon you actually got six
yeah so you you you done messed up right
thank god i feel good and since we're
here one tablespoon equals about 15
grams
of salt or about six grams of sodium
alright
so again you shot for five grams of salt
because you water one teaspoon you
actually picked up a tablespoon and you
got
15. oops triple the amount
no good a lot of the times i will talk
about this in terms of a pinch of salt
and so you may be wondering yourself
like well how much is that in fact i
think i said earlier i'll just put a
pinch of salt in your liter
well that's somewhere usually in the
neighborhood of two to four hundred
milligrams of salt
okay so if if you go back to our
equation here and you're saying okay
i know i need two and a half
grams of salt and each pinch is say 400
in order to get that you would have to
5 exit something like that right
so five pinches of salt somewhere a lot
of times during weight cut
week like i'll tell them hey uh three
pinches of salt
in this meal three pinches in this one
two in this one one right and we can
go from there and my assumption is
there's somewhere in the neighborhood of
of that 500 milligrams at the high end
of salt for the bench now another
benefit of adding salt to your fluid
is it enhances thirst desire so water
as i mentioned water actually does the
opposite so it's kind of
counterintuitive but when you drink
water
you want to drink less water when you
add salt you want to drink more
and so remember people don't drink
enough only about half as much on their
own volition
and one of the keys we talked about the
four things in the previous video
one of them was adding more salt so that
you can track them into drinking more
water and this is exactly why
okay so let's move on to potassium you
can sort of think of this as the
opposite of sodium
it rapidly moves into the cell right
because the concentration
so it helps drive water into the icf
which is really really good right so
something we want to have part of our
equation
naturally sweet potatoes are a very
common
uh source recommendation everyone thinks
of banana but don't forget the sweet
potatoes
coconut water as you'll see in a little
bit is it extremely high concentration
of potassium
and even avocados and these are probably
the four
main places people get potassium in
their diet with the exception of
our last one
spinach that's right actually so
remember the whole popeye thing where he
has the spinach and his muscles get
larger well that's actually true right
because there's a high concentration of
potassium
in the spinach so when that comes in
like i said read the bottom rapidly
moves into the cell and drives water
into the icf
intracellular fluid goes up and you get
a pump in the muscle
right we also know of course the role of
sodium and potassium and specifically
potassium
and muscle contraction so there you go
somehow in the 1940s or
whatever the heck this was these
cartoonists
kind of nailed it right pretty dope
right
okay so the last piece then is
carbohydrate all right
so i mentioned this and we said we got
to come back to it so here's what we
know
increasing glucose in the plasma means
you increase your insulin right so you
go and have a giant
bowl of coconut water and well that's a
terrible example just
something with a lot of sugar okay you
pick your example i'm not gonna do all
the work for you okay you gotta do a
little something
we know the insulin goes way up and the
point of insulin is to drive glucose
back into the cell so we can take
advantage of this when it comes to
rehydration
so we know that glucose also takes water
with it into the cell
ah that's right so glucose itself has to
go through a transporter called glute4
but as a part of that it brings water
with it so not only do we need to
probably replace the carbohydrate that
we lost in our muscle if we've
come about dehydration from exercise but
we also know that we can trick
we can enhance the water transfer
function by bringing glucose
into the into the equation which will
pull water in
you then metabolize the glucose for
whatever reason and leaves water in the
cell so small amounts of protein
can also help in gut disturbances here
so
one of the things that i do different
than a lot of folks post
extreme dehydration and think weight cut
stuff right
it's pretty close after they get off the
scale although you don't need the
protein i actually like to give it to
them
because i feel it helps a lot with gut
disturbances so
they'll come off the scale they're going
to drink these super hydration cocktails
they mostly need water sodium potassium
right salt and chloride
and carbohydrate for store but i put
this stuff in there
again for a bunch of reasons and this
has been shown it's not just me making
it up
it helps with them not getting as much
bubble guts right they feel a lot better
and more settled
okay also with carbohydrates just like
salt people tend to like to drink more
so this is one of our two
the second of our four keys to help
people drink more water during our after
exercise it better tastes good
you add salt and sugar to something
people are gonna drink a lot more
just water maybe they drink 500
milliliters salty sugar thing
maybe 700 milliliters and boom you
solved one of your problems which is
they just don't simply drink enough
fluids so that's another reason to get
it so the general recommendation we want
is something between a five to nine
percent concentration of mostly glucose
with some fructose okay now if you go
higher than that concentration it
becomes difficult to get it out of the
stomach
okay you're also probably going to get
some gut cramping and some bubbly guts
so it's really really difficult on
especially if you're coming off of a
lung a decent amount with
low carbohydrates or are none so
higher than that actually reduces the
what we call gastric emptying so the
amount of the rate that you can get
things out
lower than that is it's not enough
carbohydrate and so it's this magical
kind of number that's been shown to be
hey somewhere
in the range of five to nine percent you
want mostly glucose
because that gets out of your stomach
pretty quickly and it goes directly into
your cells and this is exactly what
we're talking about
but you want some fructose as well and
that's because it works through a
different transporter in your stomach
and so you can actually enhance the rate
of getting carbohydrate out if you're
using both
transporters maximally rather than
trying to just jam more things through
one
okay so this is why you're going to see
most well thought through
hydration products are going to have a
combination of glucose
mostly glucose and some fructose as well
of course you can get this through food
and we'll talk about that
when we get to the end all right
so if we come back to our our picture
here um
if they are a high sweater which a lot
of the athletes do
you will actually start to see some
magnesium loss
so like i said even though magnesium
loss is
a small amount if the total amount of
sweat starts to become really really
really high
well then that small amount of magnesium
is actually starts to become a
significant number
and a lot of athletes are low in it as
it is
so i don't see actually i think so
there's some intelligence behind putting
some
magnesium in there right well we already
talked about these ones right i told you
that if you just add your salt you've
got your sodium and chloride
concentrations taken care of both in
amount
and equalness right so one part each you
got to take care of that so what i want
to do now
is cover many of the common sports
strains and electrolyte solutions and
we'll see how they start to stack up
we're going to pay attention to their
sodium potassium chloride concentrations
as well as whether or not they have
magnesium and glucose
so let's take a look at our chart here
and first i want you to think about our
example remember we're working off this
case scenario where we had 165 or so
pound athlete
he lost two liters of fluid we knew his
sweat rate and so here the absolute
amount of each of the electrolytes that
he lost okay
and we can start looking at these things
now i've put these in terms of
per two liters which would be 64 ounces
which is crazy right but that's the
amount he lost so i wanted you to see
directly for example look at the numbers
the amount of sodium in that much power
age
look at how much he lost at minimum he
probably lost
a gram or a thousand milligrams
are you going to get enough of that in
powerade not even close
in fact more likely he probably lost
somewhere between two
to three maybe even upwards of four
grams
which would be four thousand milligrams
we're nowhere near that concentration in
powerade
look at our potassium right 200 to a
thousand
we're on the low end of the spectrum no
magnesium whatsoever
and probably a good amount of
carbohydrates so
we're probably fine with the
carbohydrate load
but our classic gatorades and powerades
aren't going to hit the mark
and so this is one of the things that
we'll laugh at pretty consistently and
we see people they're using these
products for hydration
they're not terrible it's better than
pure water of course
it's pretty close right they just don't
have enough it's kind of
counterintuitive a lot of people think
oh they're too salty or they have too
much sugar
well they actually don't they don't have
enough sodium they have very very very
little potassium
and they have no magnesium they also
have the carbohydrates in a form usually
of high fructose corn syrup
which is not properly glucose and
fructose combinations
so the sugar amount is okay but it's not
an ideal type
sodium amount is okay but it's too low
potassium is all right and then no
magnesium
when we compare that to the the more
common like optimal
hydration thing that people love to use
pedialyte
okay sodium concentration is getting a
lot better and look at potassium
hey pretty good there right we've
probably nailed it a little bit but
maybe even a little bit too high though
right but it's okay
better than that than the lack of
gatorade we still run into the problem
though of no magnesium
and i would argue a little bit low
amount of carbohydrate
as well as the wrong type okay so a lot
of folks will then take pedialyte as
like a base
and then start combining with other
things like a better carbohydrate source
or something with magnesium or some
additional water to kind of hit your
combination
all right so in general if you look
across the research and all and a bunch
of different sports drink products i
just highlighted three here not to pick
on them but
they usually only have somewhere between
10 to 25 of the needed sodium
so they're not going to cut it in theory
you could take your gatorade sprinkle it
with a little bit of salt and that would
help
a lot but
we can probably do better than that all
right
if we go to the next things now these
would be more sort of natural hydration
solutions
that people like coconut water being one
of the more popular ones
and what you may not realize is milk now
i know you're thinking yourself like
there's no way i'm going to come off of
a soccer field and drink some milk
i get it think of this as probably like
post exercise hydration solutions or
pre rather than ones you would drink in
a game okay but let's take a look at it
let's go with coconut water
like i said it has a mega concentration
of potassium so you're going to rock the
socks off of potassium you're going to
be good there right
maybe too much though if left on its own
right because we talked about
remember potassium helps you pee too so
perhaps not
optimal too low salt no magnesium
and actually a good and a good form
right because you're going to get that
fructose so it's a good form of
carbohydrate
so we kind of nail it there but we don't
have a thing
so one solution would be to take your
coconut water add some salt to it
and then dilute it down a little bit so
add a lot of salt add a little back
maybe even add additional more
carbohydrate to it and you're in a
pretty good spot right now if you were
to just take some straight coconut water
you'd be okay
especially if you added some salt to it
right but there we are
well if we look at milk actually it's
pretty damn good and in fact more recent
studies in the last year or two have
shown that
it it pretty much rocks the socks off of
hydration we
always knew it was good for things like
muscle recovery but hydration
is really quite impressive the way that
it works it still to me is low on salt
it has a lot of potassium and now take a
look at it boom
we're starting to crush that magnesium
source right the type of carbohydrate is
perfect
we're talking dissect well it's not
perfect it's very very very good
right it has sucrose in there which is
glucose and fructose has some other
stuff so it's in a really good spot
all right so honestly if you're like i
only want to drink natural things
this this is probably your best bet the
last category i want to cover are the
hydration
packs so these things don't really work
in terms of you don't buy them as rtds
or ready to drinks you buy them as
packets and add water to them
so what i did is i gave you these in
their serving
packets you would have to mix multiple
of these up to get to that area okay
but it depends on the size you get
because they come in small big ones or
so
it's for concentration but let's take a
look at them okay
like i said here an ounce per packet or
tablet
usually per 16 ounces this is usually
how you can
figure out the map okay if you wanted to
make
64 ounces though you just say take four
noon packs
or whatever you're going to do there so
it's easy to scale up
in fact i'll sort of jump the gun here a
little bit but this is one of the
reasons why i like these products
a lot more than these products for
hydration
because one i can specifically and
fairly easily control the concentration
and amount
okay i can't do that i can't dilute
these things anymore here all i can do
is kind of start adding salt
it also has no processing has nothing
else in them
and i can combine them i can make
combinations so i can take a serolite
and add that to coconut water oh i can
take a drip drop
and put that in with some pd light or
something like that right or just more
water
whatever so it gives you a lot more
flexibility which helps you
individualize and personalize your
approach
so if we start taking a look at each one
of these hydration packs individually
we see different pros and cons so there
may be different ones that you pick for
different athletes for example
you may be in a situation where you want
some of these things but you want no or
very little carbohydrate
okay and there could be situations like
that in that case you might go with the
noon pack right you know it's very low
in concentration it's basically all salt
you can see that between these three
ones they make
you know they're pretty equivalent in
terms of their amount of sodium and
potassium
noon and drip drop have a little bit of
magnesium and you can see sterilite
and drip drop have a little more
carbohydrate serolite specifically is a
very good con
carbohydrate source it's a rice based
thing it digests extremely well and very
very quick it actually
um it will give you no cramping
whatsoever i promise you
it'll go right out it won't even go to
the large intestines it'll get out right
through
the first part of your digestion and it
works very very very well
new serolite also makes a this called
the 70 because that's the
osmolality of the salt concentration but
they make higher ones as well
i don't believe drip drop nor noon um
allow you to do that but cerelite has
different kind of combinations
bigger packs smaller packs that if you
need a lot of it not just in size but
again in concentration
and then of course there's a new one on
the market just in the last year called
element
um and you can see that actually i like
it a lot
so to me this is i don't have any
affiliation with them whatsoever
um but to me i think they've they've got
the system a little bit better they've
got the concentrations right
a lot more sodium in them to the
equivalent you see actually they have a
five to one potassium to sodium ratio so
it's a little bit high but hey
that's totally fine a lot better than
these ones that are more like two to one
in addition
they've got a lot of magnesium in them
the downside is they have no
carbohydrate
okay so when i use element and i've used
in the past i always add a carbohydrate
source for the sake of hydration now i
don't
think they made their products
specifically for hydration
like posterior i think they made it for
sort of like daily
hydration so in that case they didn't
want to add sugar to it
i'm sure all these companies have
different rationales why they made their
products
the way they are i don't ever like to
think about things as being bad or good
i just want to know what's
in them how they work and now i can use
them to my advantage
right so i have used all of these
products numerous times
with great success okay i will look at
the individual
i'm working with figure out what do they
like personally what do they know what
are they used in the past
what do they have access to what do
their teammates like all these things
right and then i'll say okay great you
like pd light
okay great well i know pd lights got
here and here here but the downside is
this so
hey can we take a pedialyte and can we
add um maybe some noon to it
oh great yeah why because it's easily
mixed in there be a little more salt we
would
we would be in a fine position there we
would dilute it a little bit with some
water
hey in fact maybe we would add some
coconut water to it
right potassium would get really high up
there or maybe we add something else
maybe we take some honey and drizzle it
in there get some more carbohydrate
there's lots of ways you can go about it
this is i know it's kind of frustrating
because when people watch these videos
they're like
tell me the thing at this amount of
business and i hate doing that because i
don't ever do that personally
i never have like a system i can people
oh buy andy's
weight cut and rehydration thing and i
don't do that i always say what do you
have what do you like boom okay well we
have this and this is there let's add
more of this
oh that tasted terrible or i tried the
noon in it man i didn't like it at all
my stomach okay great
let's try cellulite okay boom everyone
responds differently
to these things so you have to try
different combinations and then adjust
according to what you have sometimes
it's just salt water
sometimes just salt in in coconut water
i mean there's lots of ways we can go
about it so learn the concepts learn the
science
and then memorize this chart print it
out keep it with you i don't care
put in your back pocket as a note card
walk around with it you know so you know
what to do with your athletes
you use it however you want for that
record tell me i'm wrong come back and
tell me
you've tried this before and it didn't
work or this one's right
i'm open to all these things right i'm
just trying to help you along your path
okay so now coming back to our original
thing like i mentioned at the beginning
i don't want you to guess here i want
you to assess so let me show you how you
can actually do that
first and foremost it comes trial and
error every single time i've worked with
an athlete on weight cut stuff
rehydration
they i always tell them i can't
guarantee it's gonna be perfect first
time
but i'll make i'll probably guarantee
it's gonna start to get real real real
good by times two three and four
because everyone's system works a little
bit differently
so we have to figure that out a little
bit so step number one is trial and
assess so
pick a combination weigh yourself pre
and post figure out how much you lost
and then
try something here then try other ones
try a lot on yourself try it on your
athletes and try different things
that's going to give you by far your
most accurate information
okay that's finally part two
all right so for those of you that
missed part one of our series we talked
about how much
water to drink throughout the day part
two was how much to drink
during your workout and now part three
will finally hit replenishing your
fluids post workout
now in order to do that i just got done
saying don't guess let's assess
here's what you do and i've sort of
alluded to this already
in video one i talked about these all
these units here and how
some of these you can use in your own
home or if you're more scientific or
have a bigger budget you can go to that
but you can combine all these with a
simple weight test so
just take yourself totally naked
and get on a scale put your clothes back
on don't forget this part
then go do your workout take all your
clothes back off dry your hair if you
have a lot of hair whatever happens to
be
and then weigh yourself again make sure
you wipe the water off right
if you start at 170 pounds and now
you're 166.6 pounds then you know you've
lost 3.4 pounds
right yes 3.4 pounds
then you know your sweat rate right how
well sorry time the amount of workout
right was it 45 minutes hour 25 divided
by whatever
or multiply it by whatever time domain
you use and now you figure out your
hour sweat leg rate rate per hour don't
forget though to account for the amount
of fluids you drink during the exercise
so if you lost 3.4 pounds but you drank
one pound of water 16 ounces during the
workout you actually lost 4.4 pounds
because you've already brought a water a
pound back okay so that figure
that factor that in your equation it's
easy math
and then you're good so now you've got a
better indication both directly
of how much you're losing you can know
more specifically your hydration status
in the morning and everything else right
but in this case we're talking about pre
and post workout
and then if you can scrounge up one of
these hydration tests and you can get a
patch on yourself and figure out what's
the concentration of the electrolytes in
your sweat then you start to have a real
good damn idea
of how to optimize your hydration okay
now of course in our laboratory we
always use something like this right so
we would have them do this test
go to their workout and do that
afterwards but if you only have access
to the scale
that's pretty darn good too honestly
okay
and then you can deploy what we call the
little john what
system okay you can see the article here
if you want to read more about it called
am i drinking enough yes no or maybe um
this is by bob kennedy
bob is just a legend in hydration um a
super sweet guy
really really nice and has just done a
ton of stuff in this work
so he and his colleague at the army came
up with this um
and they came up with a system called
the wut right now this is in combination
i believe with gatorade
but it basically said this w for weight
u for urine
and t for thirst and so every day in the
morning you check your weight
you do the urine thing i talked about in
video one as well as the thirst you
could also do this pre and post exercise
and here's what it's basically going to
tell you imagine a venn diagram
okay if you had two of these things show
up
then you're likely dehydrated so for
example
you've lost a significant amount of
weight and you are
uh your urine is not optimally covered
but you're not necessarily you don't
feel like the thirst hasn't gone down
you're still probably likely if you only
have one of these three
you may or may not be dehydrated two or
more
chances go up right so the same could be
combination urine looks great but your
weight
has gone down and you're thirsty or this
third combination which is urine's color
thirst is up but weight's fine
all three of those combinations of twos
probably mean you're likely dehydrated
if you have all three it's extremely
likely that you're dehydrated
okay so our post exercise fluids
should be in summary here around 125 to
of the fluid that was actually lost so
if you've lost
four pounds you need to drink back
six or so five to six pounds back in
okay
now a lot of people like 125 better i
think it's probably more realistic
but you could go up to 150 that'd be
just fine too right but a lot of people
will say they like 125 better i'm cool
with that
okay let's end here on a massive summary
the entire video series
i'm going to also make sure you feel
comfortable with your recommendation of
exactly what to do
so first and foremost i recommend that
you wake up and
as soon as you wake up in the morning
just chug some water okay
or close wake up check your phone or
whatever thing but
point is get started with your hydration
right um now i will typically drink a
full glass
of water i have this kind of ready by my
bed in the morning i wake up and it's
literally the first thing i do i get
down a full glass
of fluids now i'm only
165 pounds or so so if you're 200 pounds
maybe you need two of those things uh
scale up and down point is i get
hydration going
very first thing in the morning before i
even get up and use the bathroom
like that first thing that happens okay
number two eat mostly whole real foods
especially fruits and vegetables and
salt them liberally
right don't hesitate to do that the more
you exercise the more you sweat
the more that i'll salt my food number
three pre-hydrate
so you wanna drink at minimum half your
body weight
right in pounds in ounces a day of just
water intake
so we talked about that already and
adjust the amount based on your context
so like i said your lifestyle humidity
genetics temperature
etc and then use that what system we
talked about to figure that out
right if you're failing the what system
you're not drinking enough pure water
if you're good you pass your hydration
you pass your thirst
urine and weight
measures then you're probably in a
pretty good spot for your daily water
consumption
if you miss it then you want to hit
somewhere in the neighborhood of four to
six hundred milliliters of cool
water which is you know 16 ounce bottle
it's an aquafina bottle a normal one or
something like that
at least two to three hours prior and
then another one to three hundred or so
milliliters which is five to ten ounces
about 20 minutes before
i like cool because people tend to drink
more when it's cool
but you'll be in a good spot there okay
then from there what we call your
perihydrations the amount of water
or fluids to drink during the workout we
talked about taking your body weight in
pounds and dividing that number by 30
and drink that much in ounces every 15
minutes or so for most of us this is
gonna be somewhere between four to six
ounces every 15 minutes if that's sloshy
or feels hard on your stomach maybe go
down a little bit but
try not to go too far because your gut
is trainable so you will get better at
that feeling and you'll get better at
dumping it out
so if this is your first time being
really committed to hydration
and you get into it you're like oh my
gosh i feel so full of water all the
time my stomach
just give it a few weeks it will get
better okay your stomach will get used
to that it is trainable
okay within that though you want to
drink sweat which is something like a
three
to four to one right somewhere between
three and four to one ratio of sodium
to potassium plus about a five to nine
percent glucose and fructose solution
and remember the only way to get sodium
really is combined with chloride so i
don't have the chloride listed here
because you're gonna get it de facto
with
the sodium okay what would that look
like it could be coconut water plus some
salt and some honey
i love that combination personally
people tend to like it it tastes good
and they'll just
they'll just smash it down like you'll
see you'll never see an athlete drink a
liter of water faster
than that or you could do something like
an element and add some dextrose to it
you can get things like vitargo which is
a very nice
fast acting a carbohydrate source you
combine that with some element
and you're probably in a really really
excellent spot you can do other things
like serolite itself does make a
carbohydrate based product
they have some salt only ones and some
carbohydrates so those are all three
options you could consider and like i
said even within serolite they've got a
bunch of different combinations of
products
formulated specifically for that i would
stay away from the
biggs big brand general hydation trading
products like gatorade etc
um those honestly not not to go in the
wrong place here but
those companies are meant to sell
millions and millions of things for
people to sit around and drink all day
companies like sarah light element drip
drop noon
those are specifically made to actually
hydrate people and a lot of the cases
like in saralite
those are made for military folks so
they really have a different goal in
mind and when you're trying to max your
hydration
let's go with the companies who are
honestly trying to maximize hydration
not the ones that are just
selling sugar products to 12 year olds
okay from there
assess your sweat content if you can and
or at least experiment with the
aforementioned sweat so try different
combinations of these things at
different concentrations as well
until you can find a sweet spot and then
lastly
post hydration drink your take your body
weight pre and post
figure out how much you actually lost
and then drink at least 125
of that total amount of the same thing
that you just drank for your parry
workout okay
if you do all five of these things i
guarantee you you will crush
your hydration game right so hopefully
you enjoyed this series i know it's a
long haul
some of you may have gotten his
apartment like i didn't need to know
that in fact you may be thinking
why the hell didn't you just make this a
five minute video and jump straight to
this slide
i don't know maybe if if you really want
um i'll do that or maybe i'll do that
anyways
but you know look the reason i make
these videos is to give you answers but
also to teach you physiology and
chemistry and now you know how to count
and convert from your ounces to your
milligrams and all kinds of stuff and
he'll just make your life even better
all right so i appreciate oh wait a
minute
friends we are not done we have one more
item we have yet to accomplish
that's right friends it is time for our
fifth criminally rated under
underrated mc and that is my main man
r.a the rugged man
all right uh go look up his story he is
legendary he was
uh i'd say like a bit of a savant or a
phenom in the early 90s as a kid
and had all kinds of crazy stuff happen
to him
and a legendary guy he was around in the
early early ages but is still just
murdering the microphone to this day in
fact his best work i think has happened
in the last three or four years
despite him being sort of an underground
hip-hop legend so
uh i don't know anyone really super
active in the game that
epitomizes the lyricism better he takes
it very serious
different techniques fast low like a
cadence this is his game so if you
appreciate lyricism uh ra the rugged man
is is quite the person uh i would
recommend this is off the cuff here
if you wanted to start i would look up
his guest oh in fact
oftentimes folk folks will call his
verse on
vinnie paz's song uncommon valor one of
the best guest appearances
in hip-hop history so start with
uncommon valor and then maybe work
yourself to definition of a wrap blow
which is his sort of way to teach you
what rap lyricism should be all about
but nonetheless
now we're done all right you can go back
to whatever you're doing and yes i
promise you students
there will be extensive numbers of
questions regarding our five
most or five criminally not necessarily
most but five criminally rated nc's mcs
on all of your quizzes and tests in fact
i'm not sure i'm even asking anything
about hydration
i may just ask you questions about
hip-hop
all right thanks for staying around i
really enjoyed this stuff i hope you did
too
i don't ask much of you if you think
this is valuable
share it around if not enjoy for your
own damn self you selfish
little jerk all right i'm gonna go play
with my kids if you didn't hear scream
in the background
see you later everyone